Okay, we pick up today's דף מ"ז, Daf Mem Zayin, מ"ז. Mem
Zayin. We pick up on מ"ו עמוד ב', Mem Vav Amud Bet,
we're about 20 lines from the bottom. תנו רבנן, Tanna Rabbanan, הרב
לתלמיד. HaRav LeTalmid. We're talking about the מצוה Mitzvah of לויה Levayah
of accompanying somebody out of the city, somebody who's visiting, based on
the whole declaration of the סנהדרין Sanhedrin by the עגלה ערופה, Egla
Arufah, that or the elders of the city that our hands did
not spill this blood, meaning we were not negligent of accompanying him
out of the city, which was part of a larger discussion of
things that have to be said in Hebrew. Okay, so תנו רבנן,
Tanna Rabbanan, הרב לתלמיד, HaRav LeTalmid, even if somebody's student is visiting
them, they have an obligation to accompany the student out of the
city. And how far is that? עד עיבורה של עיר, Ad Ibburah
Shel Ir, until the pregnancy of the city, meaning until the outer
houses of the city, and there's a whole way of measuring this
for תחום שבת, Techum Shabbos, which is 2,000 אמות Amot from the
last house, and the last house is even a little house that's
within about 150 feet or so from, you know, the edges of
the normal buildup of the houses. So until the last house of
the city. עד עיבורה של עיר. Ad Ibburah Shel Ir.
חבר לחבר, Chaver LeChaver, if it's somebody who's on your equal level,
עד תחום שבת, Ad Techum Shabbos, until the תחום שבת, Techum Shabbos,
2,000 אמות Amot beyond that, about a kilometer.
עד תחום שבת. Ad Techum Shabbos.
And now the גמרא Gemara continues. תלמיד לרב, Talmid LeRav, if a
תלמיד Talmid is accompanying his רבי, Rebbe, so obviously he owes him
a whole service of כבוד הרב. Kevod HaRav. So אין לו שיעור,
Ein Lo Shiur, then you have no limit. You have to accompany
him forever, but not really forever, because it's a hilarious גמרא. Gemara.
Right after it says אין לו שיעור, Ein Lo Shiur, it says,
okay, אין לו שיעור וכמה? Ein Lo Shiur Vekama? So how much
really is it? Okay, there's got to be some limit. אמר רב
ששת, Amar Rav Sheshet, עד פרסה. Ad Parsah. פרסה. Parsah. פרסה Parsah
is four מיל, Mil, which is like four kilometers. All right, so
three times more than the תחום שבת. Techum Shabbos. ולא אמרן אלא
ברבו שאינו
מובהק, Velo Amran Ela Berabbo She-eino Muvhak, and that limit of a
פרסה, Parsah, you know, four kilometers, is only by your רבי Rebbe
who's not like your main רבי. Rebbe. אבל רבו מובהק, Aval Rabbo
Muvhak, but your רבי מובהק, Rebbe Muvhak, שלש פרסאות, Shalosh Parsaot, three
times that. 12 kilometers. That's a pretty significant amount. What is that,
like about seven miles or something? רב כהנא הוי מלוה לרב שימי
בר אשי Rav Kahana Hevei Melavei LeRav Shimi Bar Ashi מפום נהרא
עד בי תיניסא. MiPum Nahara Ad Bei Tinisa. רב כהנא Rav Kahana
accompanied רב שימי בר
אשי Rav Shimi Bar Ashi מפום נהרא, MiPum Nahara, which was a
city, to בי תיניסא Bei Tinisa דבבל, DeBavel, this place where there
was a lot of palm trees in בבל. Bavel. It was a
particular location. כי מטו התם, Ki Matu Atam, when they got to
this place, אמר ליה, Amar Lei, ודי אמרי הני תיניסא דבבל משני
אדם הראשון
נינהו. Vadi Amrei Hanei Tinisa DeBavel MiShenei Adam HaRishon Inhu. You know,
ah, these, like apparently it was some very distinctive sight, and this
big collection of palm trees, and he said, oh, this is what
people say, that these palm trees of בבל, Bavel, these were all
goes all the way back to the time of אדם הראשון. Adam
HaRishon. אמר ליה, Amar Lei, so he responded, אדכרן מילתא, Idkeran Milta,
you know what, by mentioning אדם הראשון, Adam HaRishon, you reminded me
of a nice תורה Torah point. דאמר רבי יהושע בן חנינא, DeAmar
Rabbi Yehoshua Ben Chanina, מאי דכתיב, Mai DeKetiv, what's meant by the
verse, בארץ לא עבר בה איש ולא ישב אדם שם, BeEretz Lo
Avar Bah Ish Velo Yashav Adam Sham, in a land that a
person never passed through and an אדם Adam never dwelt there? וכי
מאחר שלא עבר היכן ישב? Vekee Meachar SheLo Avar Heichan Yashav? If
nobody ever passed through it, why did the end of the verse
have to say nobody settled? Of course nobody settled, nobody passed through
it. You know, that's a classic sort of way of Hebrew poetry
operates, sometimes it sort of goes, you know, anti-climactic,
it says the thing that was already obvious in the first one.
But anyway, but that's the question being asked here. אלא ארץ שגזר
עליה אדם הראשון לישוב נתיישבה ושלא גזר עליה אדם הראשון לא נתיישבה.
Ela Eretz SheGazar Aleiha Adam HaRishon Leyishuv Nityashva VeSheLo Gazar Aleiha Adam
HaRishon Lo Nityashva.
So it's going to read the word אדם Adam literally. A man
that nobody passed through and אדם Adam was not ישב שם, Yashav
Sham, did not decree that that would be an area that would
be settled, only if אדם Adam had decreed which areas of the
globe would be settled, those are the ones that eventually were settled.
So this is sort of sharing with us how, you know, you
accompany two תלמידי חכמים Talmidei Chachamim are going, a רב Rav and
a תלמיד, Talmid, תלמיד Talmid and
רבי, Rebbe, and that ultimately it leads to even idle sort of
talk, I guess eventually leads to some degree of תורה Torah that
gets shared between them. רב מרדכי הוי מלוה לרב אשי מהגרוניא Rav
Mordechai Hevei Melavei LeRav Ashi MeHagronya ועד בי, מהגרוניא ועד בי כיפי,
VeAd Bei MeHagronya VeAd Bei Kifei, ואמרי לה עד בי דורא. VeAmrei
Lei Ad Bei Dura. רב מרדכי Rav Mordechai accompanied רב אשי Rav
Ashi מהגרוניא MeHagronya ועד בי כיפי, VeAd Bei Kifei, until place בי
כיפי, Bei Kifei, ואמרי לה עד בי דורא, VeAmrei Lei Ad Bei
Dura, and some say until this other place בי דורא. Bei Dura.
אמר רבי יוחנן משום רבי מאיר, Amar Rabbi Yochanan MiShum Rabbi Meir,
רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan said in the name of רבי מאיר, Rabbi
Meir, כל שאינו מלוה ומתלוה, Kol She-eino Melaveh U-mitlaveh, anybody who does
not accompany or does not is not accompanied, כאילו שופך
דמים, Ke-ilu Shofech Damim,
is as if they spilled blood. So the מתלוה Mitlaveh is pretty
interesting, because, you know, presumably you're the one who's being accompanied, you
don't want it, maybe it means if you refuse the accompaniment, okay,
you're also responsible if you're the one refusing. But okay, if you
and this ties clearly back to the whole story of what do
you call it, of the עגלה ערופה, Egla Arufah, where we see
that if you're not accompanying somebody it could lead to them feeling
vulnerable, being seen as vulnerable, open to attack, and so on. But
now we're going to tie it into another story in the תנ"ך.
Tanach. כאילו שופך דמים. Ke-ilu Shofech Damim. שאילמלא ליוו אנשי יריחו
לאלישע,
She-ilmalei Livu Anshei
Yericho Le-Elisha, had the people of, if only the people of יריחו
Yericho had accompanied אלישע, Elisha, לא גירה דובים בתינוקות, Lo Gira Dubim
BeTinokot, he would not have sicked the bears on the young kids,
שנאמר, Shene-emar, as the... The גמרא Gemara *Gemara* in סוטה Sotah, *Sotah*
says regarding a story in the תנ"ך *Tanakh*, כאילו שופך דמים *k'ilu
shofech damim*. שאילמלא ליווהו אנשי יריחו Yericho לאלישע *she'ilmalei livuhu anshei yericho
l'elisha*, if only the people of יריחו *Yericho* had accompanied אלישע Elisha
*Elisha*, לא גירה דובים לתינוקות *lo girah dubim l'tinokos*, he would not
have sicked the bears on the young kids, שנאמר shenemar *shenemar*, as
the verse says, ויעל משם בית אל *vaya'al misham beis el*, אלישע
Elisha *Elisha* was going from יריחו *Yericho* to בית אל *beis el*,
והוא עולה בדרך *v'hu oleh baderech*, and he was going on his
way and he was alone, and what happened because he was alone?
נערים קטנים יצאו מן העיר *ne'arim ketanim yatze'u min ha'ir* and these,
you know, younger children came out of the city, or young men,
we'll talk about that in a minute, ויתקלסו בו *v'yitkalsu bo*, and
they, you know, and they cursed him out, ויאמרו לו עלה קרח
Korach עלה קרח *vayomeru lo alei kerei'ach alei kerei'ach*, get out of
here you baldy, get out of here baldy. So אמרו לו *amru
lo*, so now what is this קרח *kerei'ach*, why are they calling
him baldy? And why were they anyway cursing him? שהקרחת לנו את
המקום *shekeirachta lanu es hamakom*. Get out of here that you have
like stripped the place because the story was that he went to
יריחו *Yericho* and they told the people told him that there the
water was bitter and he and he did a miracle and the
water became sweet and these, again this is now being that's in
the תנ"ך *Tanakh* and now being filled in by the גמרא Gemara
*Gemara*, you know these young men they would make money by selling
good water to the people of the city. So they were basically
saying you have stripped this place of our livelihood because you have
now improved the water of the city. Okay. מאי נערים קטנים *mai
ne'arim ketanim*?
So now what is meant from נערים קטנים *ne'arim ketanim*? Because נער
*na'ar* is like a young man, קטנים *ketanim* is like a kid.
So אמר amar, רבי אלעזר *amar rebbi eliezer* שמנוערים מן המצוות קטנים
שהיו מקטני אמנה *shemenu'arim min hamitzvos ketanim shehayu m'katnei emunah*. So they're
called נערים *ne'arim* young men because from the word they were like
emptied from מצוות *mitzvos*, they were people of no, you know, no
serious commitment to מצוות *mitzvos*, which is why they, you know, were
mistreated the נביא *navi* this way and קטנים *ketanim* that they were
of little faith. Ye of little faith because they were just because
now they wouldn't be able to make money by selling good water,
you know they should have had faith in God that God would
have find another way for them to have been provided for. Okay
so anyway the point is that here you see and this is
why I probably said earlier מלווה ומתלווה *m'laveh umisla'veh* because it wasn't
אלישע Elisha *Elisha* that himself was in endangered because you know it
wasn't like he died, it was the kids died because he got
angry at them and he sicked the kids on them. So both
the people of יריחו *Yericho* didn't accompany him and he who did
not maybe insist on accompaniment or agreed to it or whatever, both
of them were were held responsible for what resulted that because of
his vulnerability he was attacked but that ultimately resulted in him attacking
them, not verbally but through these bears and then and then they
were killed. We'll see forty-two of them were killed of these young
men. Okay. תנא *tana* and the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is holding him
and the people of יריחו *Yericho* liable for that, responsible for that.
תנא נערים היו *tana ne'arim hayu*, they were young men, again dealing
with the נערים *ne'arim* and the קטנים *ketanim*, ובזבזו עצמם כקטנים *uvizbezu
atzmam k'ketanim*, but they treated themselves like you know like kids, they
were acting like like children that they were like mocking the נביא
*navi*. Okay. אמתקיף לה רב יוסף *amskif lah rav yosef*. רב יוסף
*Rav Yosef* challenged. You're bothered by the word נערים *ne'arim* and קטנים
*ketanim*? I have another explanation for the word נערים *ne'arim*. ודילמא על
שם מקומן *v'dilma al shem mekoman*? Maybe they're called נערים *ne'arim* because
they came from there's a place called that that would that that
that should be their name. Why? דמניעורין הוו *d'min'urin havu*? There's a
place called נעורין *Ne'urin* and that's why they're נערים *ne'arim*, people from
נער *Na'ar*, not that they were young men.
So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says על שם מקומן *al shem mekoman*.
I'm sorry I skipped a line. על שם מקומן *al shem mekoman*?
מי mi. לא כתיב *mi lo kesiv*, is it not written וארם
יצאו גדודים וישבו מארץ ישראל Yisrael, נערה קטנה *v'aram yatze'u gedudim vayishbu
m'eretz yisrael na'ara ketana*? And so ארם *Aram* took captive from from
land of Israel a young lass נערה *na'ara*, but נערה *na'ara* again
is a young woman, קטנה *ketana* is a child. So קשיא לה
נערה וקטנה *kashya lah na'ara v'ketana*, how could it be both? Same
like the question here. So ואמר רב פדת *v'amar rav pedas* קטנה
דמנעורין *ketana d'min'urin*. No it was a young child from a place
called נעורין *Ne'urin*. נערה *na'ara* means from this place. So maybe here
too they were from this place and it doesn't mean they were
young men? No. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says התם לא מפרש
מקומה *hasam lo mefareish mekoma*. There you can say נערה *na'ara* means
from the place of נעורין *Ne'urin* because it doesn't say where she
came from. הכא מפרש מקומו *hacha mefareish mekumo* and here it says
their place. It says that they were from יריחו *Yericho*. Okay, going
continuing with this story with אלישע Elisha. *Elisha* and the children. ויפן
אחריו *vaya'fen acharav* and he turned behind him to see these children
mocking him ויראם *vaya'ram* and he saw them ויקללם *vayakallem* and he
cursed them בשם ה' *beshem hashem* in God's name. מאי ראה *mai
ra'ah*? What is meant just he looked at them? Like he looked,
what do you mean he looked? Just he saw them? So אמר
רב ראה ממש *amar rav ra'ah mamash*, it just literally, it doesn't
mean anything it means he looked. I mean we'll see how that
contrasts to other explanations. כדתניא רבי שמעון גמליאל אומר *k'dsanya rebbi shimon
gamliel omer* כל מקום שנתנו חכמים עיניהם או מיתה או עוני *kol
makom shenasnu chachamim eineihem o misa o oni*. Whenever the rabbis give
like their evil eye, you know, they put their eye against somebody
that they're mad at and they want him to be punished, he'll
either die or become poor. So yes it means a look, but
a look from this נביא *navi* is going to bring with it
the disaster that it brought. ושמואל אמר *u'shmuel amar*, no, ראה שכולן
נתעברה בהן אמן ביום הכיפורים *ra'ah shekulan nisabra bahen imman b'yom hakippurim*.
So now we're going to have other reads which are going to
try to somewhat mitigate how bad it was when אלישע Elisha *Elisha*
did. I mean it's still bad, but the גמרא Gemara, *Gemara* is
trying to sort of say you know maybe to some degree we
can make our peace with this because it's sort of like משה
*Moshe*, you know what it says ויפן כה וכה וירא כי אין
איש *vaya'ifen koh vakoh vaya'ra ki ein ish*, he saw that no
righteous person would come from this מצרי *mitzri*, but that means he
was literally the process of maybe killing a Hebrew. Anyway here it
says he saw that you know that they were all born in
sin, all of them their mothers had become impregnated with them on
יום כיפור *Yom Kippur* meaning that their mothers had sex on יום
כיפור *Yom Kippur*. Of course, why that means that they deserve to
die is not so clear. Okay, רבי יצחק נפחא Rabbi Yitzchak Nafcha
אמר, so רבי יצחק נפחא is now going to try to do
it to make it even more a little bit make our peace
with why they died. בלורי סתרא להן, Blurei stara lehen, he saw
that they had their hair cut in a particular type of a
haircut כאמוראים, kaamorayim, which was a way like was like the Amorites,
like the people of the, you know, of the Canaanites who lived
there. Maybe it shows that they were idolaters or whatever, they were
not so frum. Okay,
רבי יוחנן אמר ראה שלא היתה בהן לחלוחית של מצוה. Rabbi Yochanan
amar ra'ah shelo hayta bahen lachluchit shel mitzvah. He saw that they
had, they were empty, they didn't even have any little moisture of
מצוה, mitzvah, they were completely empty of מצות. mitzvot. And again, not
saying that that justified his actions, the גמרא Gemara clearly is critical
of his actions but maybe makes it somewhat more tolerable. ודילמא בזרעיהו
ניהוי. Vedilma bezara ayhu nihavi. Okay, maybe they didn't have מצות, mitzvot,
but maybe they would have given birth to children that would have
you know had מצות. mitzvot. How can we really make our peace?
I mean it's a tragedy. You take one life, all the future
generations. אמר רבי אלעזר לא בם ולא בזרעם עד סוף כל הדורות.
Amar Rabbi Elazar lo bam velo bezaram ad sof kol hadorot. No,
he saw that never in any of the future generations would anything
good come of them. You know, גמרא Gemara often says the exact
opposite, right? Like you know even the grandchildren you know of קרח
and whatever and נבוכדנצר, Nebuchadnezzar, etc. So,
but nevertheless, here it's trying to at least mitigate how bad it
was what אלישע Elisha did. Okay, ותצאנה שתים דבים מן היער, vatetzeina
shtayim dubim min haya'ar, and two bears came out of the forest,
ותבקענה בהם ארבעים ושנים ילדים, vativakana bahem arbaim ushnayim yeladim, and it
burst through them meaning you know and it mauled forty-two of the
children. רב ושמואל, Rav uShmuel, אדיבי דרב ושמואל, ad'debay deRav uShmuel, חד
אמר נס וחד אמר נס בתוך נס. chad amar nes vechad amar
nes betoch nes. The one said it was just a straight miracle.
The other, no, it was a miracle on top of a miracle.
מאן דאמר נס, man de'amar nes, יער הוה, yaar hava, there was
a forest, דובים לא הוו, dubim lo havu, but there wasn't any
bears in the forest. So he not only did he make the
bears come out, bears appeared where never there had been bears before.
That was the miracle. מאן דאמר נס בתוך נס, man de'amar nes
betoch nes, the one that said it was a miracle built on
a miracle, לא יער הוה ולא דובים הוו. lo yaar hava velo
dubim havu. There were neither before he he you know called upon
this miracle to happen, there was neither a forest nor bears. So
first he made the forest and then he made the bears in
the forest to come out and to maul them. So now the
גמרא Gemara says, ולהוי דובים ולא להוי יער, v'lehavi dubim velo lehavi
yaar, you know like who needs the forest? Just make the bears,
okay, granted if there was already a forest, fine, but if but
according to the position that he did two miracles, why not just
make the bears? So you can give the answer, well he wanted
to make it look more natural, so you needed a forest for
them to come from. But that's not the answer the גמרא Gemara
says. The גמרא Gemara says דבעיתי. de'bi'isi. No, because if there wouldn't
be a forest, then the bears would be afraid that they wouldn't
attack because they they would only attack humans if they had a
place to run to, to hide afterwards. So it's interesting even with
the miracle of the forest and the bears, the bears are going
to still act like normal bears. Okay. אמר רבי חנינא בשביל ארבעים
ושנים קרבנות שהקריב בלק מלך מואב. Amar Rabbi Chanina bishvil arbaim ushnayim
korbanot shehikriv Balak melech Moav. Now we're going to deal with the
fact that the forty-two of the children died.
הופקעו מישראל ארבעים ושנים ילדים. hufka miYisrael arbaim ushnayim yeladim. What you
know because of the forty-two sacrifices that בלק Balak did to curse
bring about a curse through בלעם Bilaam on ישראל, Yisrael, so he
so that you know he's seeing a correspondence of forty-two and forty-two.
So the fact that it had enough impact even though it didn't
have the evil he wanted it to have but you know that
had enough impact that it caused these forty-two deaths eventually to happen.
איני, eini, is that really true? ואמר רב יהודה אמר רב לעולם
יעסוק אדם בתורה ובמצות אף על פי שלא לשמה שמתוך שלא לשמה
בא לשמה. va'amar Rav Yehuda amar Rav le'olam ya'asok adam betorah umitzvot
af al pi shelo lishma shemitoch shelo lishma ba lishma. You should
always do תורה Torah and מצות mitzvot even for not the right
reason because even for not the right reason ultimately you know comes
to become the right reason. שבשכר ארבעים ושנים קרבנות שהקריב בלק מלך
מואב, shebischar arbaim ushnayim korbanot shehikriv Balak melech Moav, for the for
the merit of the forty-two sacrifices that בלק Balak did and that
was for the sake of hurting ישראל, Yisrael זכה ויצתה ממנו רות,
zacha veyatzta mimenu Rut, eventually you know רות Rut is מואביה Moaviyah
so רות Rut came from בלק Balak I mean she's understood her
to be a direct descendant of בלק. Balak. שיצא ממנה שלמה sheyatza
mimena Shlomo and ultimately from רות Rut came דוד David and came
שלמה Shlomo שכתוב בו אלף עלות יעלה שלמה, shekatuv bo elef olot
ya'aleh Shlomo, he brought a thousand sacrifices to God for the right
reason. So you see I mean obviously it's a little bit funny,
you know בלק Balak first of all normally when we say do
it שלא לשמה shelo lishma we say do it for maybe you
know a self-interested motive not for an evil motive. בלק Balak here
did it for an evil motive and ultimately it led to לשמה,
lishma, not his לשמה, lishma, but ultimately you know somehow that merit
brought about that his descendant did it לשמה. lishma. Anyway says the
גמרא, Gemara you see that the way this sacrifice worked is it
brought about something good, not that the efficacy that it had was
actually the bad the שלא לשמה shelo lishma efficacy. That was that
so so how does that fit with what you just said? So
the גמרא Gemara says,
אמר רב יוסף בן חוני, amar Rav Yosef ben Choni, first brings
this point, רות בתו של עגלון בנו של בלק היתה. Rut bito
shel Eglon beno shel Balak hayta. רות Ruth was the daughter of
עגלון Eglon who was the son of בלק. Balak. So anyway that's
how רות Ruth came from בלק Balak and שלמה Shlomo came from
בלק. Balak. So the גמרא Gemara says, תאותו מיהא לקללה הויא. ta'avaso
miya lekilela hava. It's true the good did come out of it,
that's the that's the לשמה lishma that came from the שלא לשמה,
shelo lishma, but because his desire was evil, that also had an
impact and that also did bring about some evil. Okay. ויאמרו אנשי
העיר אל אלישע הנה נא, va'amru anshei ha'ir el Elisha hinei na,
now we're doubling back to when אלישע Elisha came to יריחו and
he made the the water better, which ultimately this story was the
aftermath of. ויאמרו אנשי העיר אל אלישע הנה נא מושב העיר טוב
כאשר אדני ראה, vayamru anshei ha'ir el Elisha hineh na moshav ha'ir
tov ka'asher adoni ro'eh, behold the dwelling of the city is pleasant
as you see, it's a lovely city. The only problem is that
the waters are bitter, the end of the pasuk is, you know,
and והארץ משכלת, veha'aretz meshakalet, and the land causes people, you know,
the women to have to miscarry. That's it. Other than that, it's
totally fine. So the גמרא Gemara asks, he say, the גמרא Gemara
says וכי מאחר דמים רעים, vechi me'achar demayim ra'im, if the waters
are bad, והארץ משכלת veha'aretz meshakalet and the land causes miscarriage, אלא
מה טובתה, ela mah tovatas, what do you mean you see that
it's a nice city? So אמר רבי חנין, amar Rabbi Chanin,
חן מקום על יושביו, chen makom al yoshvav, it's nice, Chanin Chen.
Said Rabbi Chanin, חן מקום על יושביו. chen makom al yoshvav. You
know what? Every city looks beautiful to its inhabitants. You're living there,
you find its charms, you know, maybe it's a little bit of
a, you know, desire so it's like that you know you want
to some subconsciously, you know, since you're here anyway, you know, you
find the things that are you learn to really love it and
to find it beautiful even if from an outside perspective, there'd be
a lot to criticize. Okay. So
חן מקום על יושביו. chen makom al yoshvav. So ואמר רבי יוחנן
v'amar Rabbi Yochanan and now Rabbi Yochanan said, שלשה חינות הן, shlosha
chinot hein, there are three things of charm, you know, which maybe
is not like objectively beautiful, but it charms the person and it
makes them feel positive about it. Okay. Three things. חן אשה על
בעלה, chen isha al ba'ala, the,
the charm of a woman is on her husband, again all from
the man's perspective. So, you know, some outsider might say I don't
see what you know, I mean we can make it more balanced,
they see in one another, but they, you know, they totally seem
in love, they find, you know, so and again, maybe there's some
like cognitive dissonance here, you know, once you're married and you're in
the marriage or whatever, you find, you know, that's one way of
saying it, or maybe parts people stay in the marriage because they
stay in the city, it should do a whole psychological analysis here.
But anyway, when somebody's in that situation, they are in their eyes,
you know, it's sort of like, you know, in their eyes they
find favor with their situation. The favor, the charm of a כלה
kallah is on her husband,
חן כלה על בעלה, chen kallah al ba'ala, חן אשה על בעלה.
chen isha al ba'ala. I'm sorry. חן מקום על יושביו, chen makom
al yoshvav, the charm of a place is on those who dwell
there, חן אשה על בעלה, chen isha al ba'ala, the charm of
a woman is on her, you know, is on her husband, חן
מקח על מקחו, chen mekach al mikcho, and when you buy something,
you know, you, you know, you can think it's wonderful even again
if some outsider will say I think you got a little ripped
off or something. Okay. תנו רבנן, tanu rabanan, our rabbis taught, שלשה
חולאין חלה אלישע. shlosha cholaim chala Elisha. Elisha had three illnesses, you
know, serious sickness. אחד שגירה דובים בתינוקות, echad shegira dubim batinokot, one
was a punishment for, for sicking the, the bears on these children,
ואחד שדחפו לגיחזי בשתי ידים, ve'echad shedechafot l'Geichazi bishtei yadayim, the other
that he pushed away Geichazi with both hands, Geichazi who went ran
after Naaman who was cured from his leprosy and in order to
receive some reward and, you know, and Elisha curses him out. So
he pushed him away with both hands as opposed to giving him
מוסר mussar but then trying to bring him back. ואחד
שמת בו, ve'echad shemet bo, and then the third one ultimately was
not maybe a punishment, it was just he, you know, his
illness before he died. Okay. And how do we know he had
three illnesses? We don't know that, you know, the correspondence that the
גמרא Gemara says, but how does the גמרא Gemara, learn out the
idea that there were three? שנאמר as the verse says, ואלישע חלה
את חליו אשר ימות בו, v'Elisha chala et chalyo asher yamut bo,
Elisha became sick the illness in which he would die by. So
the גמרא Gemara. reads there are three. חלה chala became sick, חליו
chalyo his sickness, אשר ימות בו asher yamut bo the thing ultimately
that would kill him, there were three times he became seriously ill.
תנו רבנן, tanu rabanan, our rabbis taught, לעולם תהא שמאל דוחה וימין
מקרבת. le'olam tehei smol docha ve'yamin mekarevet. You always should have when,
you know, you when you have to give מוסר mussar and, you
know, and criticize somebody, you should push them away with your left,
but bring them close with your right. So you don't start by
bringing them close, you know, you gotta give the מוסר, mussar, but
after you give the מוסר, mussar, your drawing them back in should
be stronger than your pushing away. Okay.
And how do we know this?
לא כאלישע שדחפו לגיחזי בשתי ידיו, lo ke'Elisha shedechafot l'Geichazi bishtei yadav,
not like do not follow the bad example of Elisha who pushed
away Geichazi with both
hands, ולא כיהושע בן פרחיה שדחפו לאחד מתלמידיו בשתי ידיו velo kiYehoshua
ben Perachia shedechafot le'echad mitalmidav bishtei yadav that pushed away one of
his students with two hands. That's the printed גרסא, girsa, the actual
גרסא girsa is לישו הנוצרי, le'Yeshu HaNotzri, pushed away Jesus with two
hands, and we'll see that the student he pushed away went ahead
and worshipped עבודה זרה avoda zara and so on. The only problem,
I mean it was changed because we did not want the church
to, you know, see this and, and censor it or burn the
תלמוד Talmud which has happened.
But the, but it's also difficult to assume it means Jesus because
Rabbi Yehoshua ben Perachia lived about 150 years before Jesus,
although which does not or maybe 100 years, excuse me, about 70
before the common era. Anyway, which doesn't mean that the גמרא Gemara
got the history right. The גמרא Gemara might have actually thought it
was Jesus, but historically it couldn't have been. Okay. אלישע מאי היא,
Elisha mai hi, what's the story with Elisha and Geichazi? דכתיב dich'tiv
the verse
says ויאמר נעמן vayamru Naaman Naaman said some type of a compensation
or of a reward after אלישע Elisha *Elisha* had said him do
that אלישע *Elisha* had made the point that we do not take
a reward here for this for having cleared up the leprosy. Okay
וכתיב *uksiv* the verse says ויאמר אליו לא לבי הלך כאשר הפך
איש מעל מרכבתו לקראתך *vayomer elav lo libi halach ka'asher hafach ish
me'al merkavto likrasecha* then when נעמן *Naaman* came when גיחזי *Geichazi* came
back and אלישע *Elisha* criticized him and אלישע *Elisha* said to him
ויאמר אליו לא לבי הלך כאשר הפך איש מעל מרכבתו לקראתך *vayomer
elav lo libi halach ka'asher hafach ish me'al merkavto likrasecha* my heart
was not with you I did not approve when that man turned
off from his chariot in order to greet you כאשר הלך איש
לקראתך *ka'asher halach ish likrasecha* sorry skipped a line מעל מרכבתו לקראתך
העת לקחת את הכסף ולקחת בגדים וזיתים וכרמים וצאן ובקר ועבדים ושפחות
*me'al merkavto likrasecha ha'eis lakachas es hakesef velakachas bgadim vezeisim u'chramim vetzon
u'vakar va'avadim u'shfachos* is now really the time to accept these types
of gifts silver and garments
and olives and vineyards and sheep and cattle and male and female
slaves. Okay so now the problem is that he only didn't take
all that stuff so the גמרא Gemara. *Gemara* says ומי שקיל כולי
האי *u'mi shakil kuli hai* did he really take all this stuff?
הכסף ובגדים הוא דשקיל *hakesef u'vgadim hu d'shakil* if you actually read
the פסוק pasuk *pasuk* the פסוק pasuk *pasuk* just says that he
took silver and garments he didn't take all that
stuff so how do you explain why all of this was mentioned?
אמר רבי יצחק *Amar Rabbi Yitzchak* באותה שעה היה אלישע עוסק בשמונה
שרצים *be'osa sha'ah hayah Elisha osek b'shmonah sheratzim* because אלישע *Elisha* had
been learning and presumably learning with גיחזי *Geichazi* until that time the
הלכות *halachos* of the שמונה שרצים *shemonah sheratzim* like the eight rodents
or whatever that cause טומאה *tuma*. אמר לו *Amar lo* רשע rasha
הגיע עת ליטול שכר שמונה שרצים *Rasha higia eis lital s'char shemonah
sheratzim*. Okay so these are eight types of things that he mentioned
the gold and the silver and the clothes etc. so he said
because of this sin any reward that you had for the תורה
Torah *Torah* you learned now you will receive it. So maybe God
now will give you clothes and sheep and cattle etc. that'll be
your reward but you're not getting עולם הבא *Olam Haba*. Okay וצרעת
נעמן *V'tzaraas Naaman* back to the פסוק *pasuk* תדבק בך ובזרעך לעולם
*tidbak becha u'vzarcha l'olam* and the leprosy the צרעת *tzaraas* of נעמן
*Naaman* because that I cleared up and now you wanted to take
this reward now it should cleave to you and your children forever.
Okay now that we had mentioned him and his children are going
to have צרעת *tzaraas* we're going to use it which the גמרא
Gemara *Gemara* does sometimes to try to explain some tie pieces of
together in various stories. So now we have a story from that
time וארבעה אנשים היו מצרעים פתח השער *V'arba'a anashim hayu m'tzoraim pesach
hasha'ar* there were four people who had צרעת *tzaraas* who were by
the gate right in this was when they ran to the besieging
army and so on and God had scared away the whole army
etc. etc. אמר רבי יוחנן זה גיחזי ושלשת בניו *Amar Rabbi Yochanan
zeh Geichazi u'shloshas banav* who are the מצרעים *m'tzoraim*? Well we already
know גיחזי *Geichazi* and his children were מצרעים *m'tzoraim* so that must
be גיחזי *Geichazi* and his three children. Okay וילך אלישע דמשק *Vayelech
Elisha Damesek* now we're going to talk about this idea that he
pushed him away with both hands so he saw he pushed him
away he only gave him very harsh מוסר *mussar* nothing positive. Now
the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is going to try to sort of also
have a poignant aftermath to this. וילך אלישע דמשק *Vayelech Elisha Damesek*
the later פסוק *pasuk* says אלישע *Elisha* went to Damascus. למה הלך
*lama halach*? Why did he go? אמר רבי יוחנן שהלך להחזירו לגיחזי
בתשובה *Amar Rabbi Yochanan shehalach lehachziro l'Geichazi b'teshuva*. He went to get
גיחזי *Geichazi* to come back to do in תשובה tshuva. *teshuva* finally
he was having some remorse אלישע *Elisha*. ולא חזר *v'lo chazar* and
he didn't he refused to come back with him. אמר לו חזור
בך *Amar lo chazor becha* so אלישע *Elisha* said please now the
חזור *chazor* here doesn't just mean physically come back it also means
like do תשובה teshuvah. *teshuva* he begged him. אמר לו *Amar lo*
so גיחזי *Geichazi* said to him כך מקובלני ממך כל מי שחטא
והחטיא את הרבים אין מספיקין בידו לעשות תשובה ein maspikin biyado la’asot
teshuvah, *kach mikublani mimcha kol mi shechata v'hichti es harabim ein maspikin
b'yado la'asos teshuva*. No you've taught me anybody that sinned and caused
others to sin he does not get the wherewithal to do תשובה
teshuvah. *teshuva* which doesn't mean it's impossible but means
it's
practically it's going to be extremely
difficult and therefore he chose to read that as
also one wonders if this teaching is part of the pushing away
with two hands because the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* teaches this point but
is this a wise thing to teach because it just slams the
door in front of people? Okay you've already taught me it's not
going to help so I'm not even going to try. Okay מאי
עביד *Mai avid*? Now where did he make other people sin that
the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* can sort of say this about him? איכא
דאמרי אבן שואבת תלה לו לחטאת ירבעם בן נבט והעמידו בין שמים
לארץ *Ika d'amri even shoevet tala lo l'chatas Yerovam ben Nevat v'amido
bein shamayim l'aretz*. So ירבעם בן נבט *Yerovam ben Nevat* made these
two golden calves and set them up to be the competing kingship
in
the other ten tribes. He went ahead to give them power he
basically put these big magnets
and with the opposite poles or with the same poles rather anyway
and it caused them to be suspended in mid-air and that made
people think they were real gods. So I don't know why we're
saying that he did this but once we say that this dynamic
was that he said he caused others to sin now we're attributing
this to גיחזי *Geichazi*. Okay that's a real החטיא את הרבים *hichti
es harabim* which maybe also shows you what happens you do a
tiny little sin a tiny little thing wrong you get pushed away
you really become להכעיס *l'hachis* and not only are you going to
leave you're going to do עבודה זרה avodah zarah. *avoda zara* you're
going to... cause other people to do עבודה זרה avodah zarah, and
it really shows you the consequence of what it means to push
people away and to not work to bring them back and also
to like slam the door with statements like nobody will be able
to
תשובה. Okay so okay ואיכא דאמרי veika damri some say שם חקק
לו אפומא shem chakak lo apuma that he actually wrote God's name
engraved it on the mouth of these golden calves והיה אומר אנוכי
ולא יהיה לך v'havah omer Anochi velo yihiye lacha and it wasn't
suspended in mid-air was maybe even worse because it magically was saying
I am the Lord your God and I have taken you out
of Egypt you should have no other gods before me I mean
oh my god think about the power that has to mislead people.
Okay okay ואיכא דאמרי veika damri רבנן דחא מקמיה rabbanan dacha mikamei
and some say and this is like a little bit parallel you
know אלישע was דוחה doche גחזי Geichazi with two hands the way
that גחזי Geichazi himself had sinned prior to being driven away was
that he pushed Rabbis away from אלישע. He wanted like a monopoly
on אלישע or he didn't want you know he only wanted a
very small number of disciples in אלישע's presence so he kept people
away from him. How do we know this? דכתיב dechesiv because it
says after גחזי Geichazi was pushed away ויאמרו בני הנביאים אל אלישע
vayomru bnei hanevi'im el Elisha the sons of the נביאים nevi'im meaning
the people that were like studying the interns the נביאים nevi'im said
to אלישע הנה נא המקום אשר אנחנו יושבים שם לפניך צר ממנו
hinei na hamakom asher anachnu yoshvim sham lefanecha tzar mimenu that it's
too crowded here there are too many
of these acolytes there are too many of these people trying to
be נביאים nevi'im so why was it so crowded? It was crowded
because גחזי Geichazi wasn't there anymore so he wasn't
there to be pushing them away. מכלל דעד האידנא michlal d'ad idna
from this you can infer that until this time לא הוה דחיק
lo hava dachek it was not crowded. Okay so that's a story
about אלישע and גחזי. Geichazi. Now יהושע בן פרחיה מאי הוה? Yehoshua
ben Prachya mai hava? What was the story about יהושע בן פרחיה?
Yehoshua ben Prachya? הוה דקא קטיל ינאי מלכא לרבנן hava d'ka katil
Yannai malka l'rabbanan when ינאי Yannai the king was killing out all
of the Pharisees all of the Rabbis שמעון בן שטח אטמיה אחתיה
Shimon ben Shetach atmitiah achtiya so שמעון בן שטח's Shimon ben Shetach
sister who was who you know who was married to ינאי Yannai
hid him. רבי יהושע בן פרחיה אזל Rabbi Yehoshua ben Prachya azal
now that was how שמעון בן שטח Shimon ben Shetach was protected.
רבי יהושע בן פרחיה Rabbi Yehoshua ben Prachya who was the
נשיא Nasi he went and אזל ערק לאלכסנדריא של מצרים azal arek
l'Alexandria shel Mitzrayim he went and he ran away to Alexandria in
Egypt. כי הוה שלמא ki hava shama then when things calmed down
שלחה ליה שמעון בן שטח. shalacha lei Shimon ben Shetach. So שמעון
בן שטח Shimon ben Shetach sent a message to רבי יהושע בן
פרחיה Rabbi Yehoshua ben Prachya מני ירושלים עיר הקודש לך אלכסנדריא של
מצרים mini Yerushalayim ir hakodesh lach Alexandria shel Mitzrayim from here from
me Jerusalem the Holy City sending a message to you Egypt אחותי
achoti my sister
Alexandria my sister
בעלי שרוי בתוכך ba'ali sharui betochech my husband is dwelling in your
midst ואני יושבת שוממה va'ani yoshevet shomema and I am desolate. So
it was like a nice little poetic message one but it was
also coded for some reason things weren't totally peaceful. Anyway anyway so
רבי יהושע בן פרחיה Rabbi Yehoshua ben Prachya got the point. אמר
שמע מינה הוה ליה שלמא amar shma mina hava lei shlama now
I see now it's peaceful. So he decided to head back to
ירושלים. Yerushalayim. כי אתא ki ata as he was on his way
back איקלע ליה אושפיזא itla lo ushpiza he came to an inn.
קמה קמיה ביקרא kama kama bei yekara
the woman who was the head of the
inn stood before him and showed him great honor שפיר עבדי ליה
עבדי ליה יקרא shapir avid lei avid lei yekara and you know
treated him very with a lot of respect properly. שפיר עבדי ליה
יקרא טובא shapir avid lei yekara tuva with great respect with great
honor. יתיב וקא משתבח yateiv veka mishtabeach and so יהושע בן פרחיה
Yehoshua ben Prachya was praising her כמה נאה אכסניא זו kama na'eh
achsanya zo
how wonderful how beautiful this is meaning how beautiful she is in
terms of her action you know what an amazing what an amazing
proprietress. אמר ליה חד מתלמידיו amar lei chad mitlamidiv
so one of his students and actually the גרסא girsa is you
know ישו הנוצרי Yeshu HaNotzri said to him רבי עיניה טרוטות Rabbi
eineiha trutot
what do you mean she's so amazing her eyes are round they're
not she doesn't have attractive eyes. So he thought you know he
interpreted it as he was talking about her appearance not about her
מדות. middos. So אמר ליה רשע בכך אתה עוסק? amar lei rasha
bekach ata osek? So יהושע בן פרחיה Yehoshua ben Prachya said רשע
rasha you know called him immediately called him a רשע that's what
you're thinking about? You know not about the way she's treating us
you're thinking about her looks? בכך אתה עוסק? bekach ata osek? אפיק
ארבע מאה שיפורי apik arba mei'ah shofrot
he took out four hundred שופרות shofrot you know which you blow
when you put somebody in חרם cherem ושמתיה v'shamtei and he put
him under the ban. כל יומא אתא לקמיה ולא קבליה. kol yoma
ata lekamei velo kiblei.
So then ישו הנוצרי Yeshu HaNotzri came back to him day after
day after day trying to be you know re-accepted by him. יומא
חד הוה קא קרי קריאת שמע yoma chad hava ka korei krias
shema then one day יהושע בן פרחיה Yehoshua ben Prachya was saying
קריאת שמע krias shema and אתא לקמיה ata lekamei
and he came to him ישו Yeshu and wanted again to try
to be accepted by him. הוה בדעתיה לקבליה hava bedaito lekablei exactly
that day
he had a change of heart and he was actually thinking you
know what maybe I should he was going to re-accept him he
was going to welcome him back. לא קבליה lo kiblei אחוי ליה
בידיה achvei lei biyadei
he motioned with his hands. סבר מדחא דחי ליה savar midche dachei
lei but that motion was was not clear what it meant and
ישו Yeshu interpreted it as
so he was saying get out of here.
you
know, or at least with the hands, gesturing away. Okay. אזל זקפה
ללבנתא, Azal zakfei livneita,
so he erected a stone, פלחא palcha and he worshipped it. He
worshipped עבודה זרה. אמר ליה חזור בך, Amar lei chazor becha, so
then יהושע בן פרחיה Yehoshua ben Perachiah came to him and said,
come, do תשובה. אמר ליה כך מקובלני ממך, Amar lei kach mekublani
mimcha, no, this is my tradition that I have, כל החוטא ומחטיא
את הרבים, kol hachotei umachti et harabbim, anybody who sins and causes
others to sin, אין מספיקין בידו לעשות תשובה, does not, you know,
allow others to do, you know, it's not given him the opportunity
to do תשובה. Now, it doesn't say here how he caused others
to sin. הגמרא's haGemara assuming it means, you know, ישו הנוצרי, Yeshu
HaNotzri, so maybe that sort of goes without saying, you know, let
all, you know, let people astray to believe in his, you know,
in his heresy. Okay.
Now, דאמר מר, de’amar mar, so now, oh, I'm sorry, jumped ahead.
It actually does say how here how he, how he led others
to sin. I skipped. דאמר מר de’amar mar as we taught, כישף
והסית והדיח והחטיא את ישראל. kishef vehisit vehidiach vehachti et Yisrael. There
you go. He did witchcraft and he seduced, meaning to עבודה זרה,
and he pushed and he caused ישראל to sin. So, with his
heresy, and again, this is why it does seem it's talking, you
know, the גמרא Gemara just has the dates wrong, people try to
claim oh can't be real ישו Yeshu because the dates are wrong.
Okay, but it calls him ישו הנוצרי Yeshu HaNotzri and it says
this at the end. Anyway, so look, you know, he created this
whole heresy and he caused all these others to sin, and therefore
he was gone and he felt he had, when finally the desire
was to bring him back, it was too late. תניא רבי שמעון
בן אלעזר אומר, Tanya Rabbi Shimon ben Elazar omer, יצר תינוק ואשה
תהא שמאל דוחה וימין מקרבת. yeitzer tinok ve’ishah tehei smol docha ve’yamin
mekarevet. Now that we have talked about pushing away with the left
and drawing close with the right when somebody deserves some criticism, now
we're sort of saying other types of like balances a person has
to do in his life. So, יצר yeitzer again, talking very much
from the man's perspective, the desire for sex, you know, you should
not try to be an ascetic, Judaism doesn't believe in that, but
you shouldn't be running after, you know, sexual pleasure all the time.
So, you should try to moderate, push away with the left but
draw close with the right. Ultimately embrace and that's really important, I
mean, that's really very, I mean, distinctive about Judaism, you know, from
a religion, the embracing of it is more powerful than the moderating
of it.
And תינוק tinok is, you know, speaking to men I guess, assuming
that the women will spend the time with the kids. So, you
know, men should be spending time, I don't know, in with their
תורה Torah or whatever. So, and you could, you know, have a
lot of fun with your kids or whatever, so and you get
carried away, so okay, moderate. But ultimately again, the right hand is
drawing close. Okay. Where were we?
And אשה, ishah, again, how exactly אשה ishah is different than the
idea of יצר yeitzer when we're talking about sex, maybe this just
means time a man spends with his wife. So, very, very interesting,
you know, from a very sort of male-dominated type of man's perspective,
you know, and so on, male-dominated society. Okay. So now we go
on to the next משנה. mishnah. Now that we're in the middle
of the discussion of עגלה ערופה. eglah arufah. נמצא ההורג עד שלא
נערפה העגלה, nimtza hahoreig ad shelo neerfah ha’eglah, if
the, if the
murderer was found before the neck was broken, תצא ותרעה בעדר, teitzei
vetireh ba’eider, then it does not have the status of עגלה ערופה
eglah arufah and it can go back and you can use it
and put it back in the flock. Now רש"י Rashi points out
that actually there's an opinion in גמרא Gemara that when it goes
down into the ואדי vadi even before the neck is broken it
becomes forbidden, but this position disagrees with it. Okay. משנערפה העגלה, misheneerfah
ha’eglah, once its neck is broken, תקבר במקומה, tikaver bimkomah, it's buried
in its place and it still remains forbidden in benefit even after
the murderer was found. Why? שעל ספק באה מתחלתה, she’al safeik ba’ah
mitchilatah, because it was coming because of the doubt, you didn't know,
couldn't find the murderer, so it served its function, it achieved atonement
for the land, not for the murderer, but you know, for the
land and somehow for the guilt that the people have, it achieved
that atonement until that punishment could be exacted on the murderer. So
מתחלה כיפרה ספיקה והלכה לה, mitchilah kiphrah sefeika vehalchah lah, so
it did the atonement it was supposed to do in that period
of doubt when you couldn't find it, it achieved its function and
therefore even though the murderer is found, it does not retroactively mean
that this was, did not do anything. No, this actually did something,
it achieved the atonement, you know, that was needed at that time.
Okay. נערפה העגלה ואחר כך נמצא ההורג. neerfah ha’eglah ve’achar kach nimtza
hahoreig. Now this is exactly the same scenario we're just talking about
but we're just sort of articulating it and by starting with the
fact that the neck was broken. First you did the עגלה ערופה
eglah arufah now you have found the murderer.
So, okay, we've discussed already the status of the עגלה eglah but
now we're going to say something else. הרי זה יהרג, harei zeh
yeihareig, in case you had any doubts, now you're going to kill
the murderer, you know who the murderer was, he doesn't get off
because you did this ritual of the עגלה ערופה. eglah arufah. עד
אחד אומר ראיתי את ההורג ועד אחד אומר לא ראיתי, לא ראית.
eid echad omer raiti et hahoreig ve’eid echad omer lo raiti, lo
raita.
One said I saw the guy who killed him. So even though
that's not enough to convict the person, if you just had one
person saying I saw the guy, then the פסוק says you do
the עגלה ערופה eglah arufah when לא נודע מי הכהו, lo noda
mi hikkahu, you don't know. If you do know, even somewhat know
because one person says, this should remind you all of what we
said about also by the case of the סוטה, sota, one person
says I saw her commit adultery, you don't make. drink the water.
The תורה Torah believed עד אחד eid echad by the סוטה, sota.
believed עד אחד eid echad by the עגלה ערופה, eglah arufah, not
believed to the point that you would convict or act on it
in a בית דין, beit din, but believe that you don't go
through with this now ritual that is because of the doubt. There
is obviously a fascinating parallel here between the עגלה ערופה eglah arufah
and the סוטה. sota So if one person says, so if the
but it's one against one though, they neutralize one another and you
go through with the process as you normally would. So עד אחד
אומר ראיתי, eid echad omer raiti, one says I saw, ואחד אומר
לא ראית, ve-echad omer lo raita, you didn't see, אשה אומרת ראיתי,
isha omeret raiti, a woman says I saw, ואשה אומרת לא ראית,
ve-isha omeret lo rait, and a woman says you didn't, היו עורפין,
hayu orfin, then they neutralize and you go like you normally would
do, you would break the neck. But if it was just one
that said I saw and nobody contradicted, you would not. עד אחד
אומר ראיתי, eid echad omer raiti, one says I saw, ושנים אומרים
לא ראית, u-shnayim omrim lo raita, two said you did not, היו
עורפין, hayu orfin, you would break the neck. I mean that's sort
of obvious based on what we just said a minute ago. שנים
אומרים ראינו, shnayim omrim rainu, two says we saw, ועד אחד אומר
לא ראיתם, ve-eid echad omer lo reitem, you did not see, לא
היו עורפין, lo hayu orfin, you wouldn't because now you have two
that says we
saw, so they beat out against the one and therefore they don't
neutralize one another and you have the weight that says that there
was a murderer and there the murderer was known even if maybe
they can't identify him but they at least saw the event happen,
we'll see about that in the גמרא, and therefore you do not
go through with the ritual. Okay.
שנים אומרים ראינו ועד אחד אומר לא ראיתם לא היו עורפין. shnayim
omrim rainu ve-eid echad omer lo reitem lo hayu orfin. משרבו הרוצחנים,
mishe-rabu ha-rotzchanim, when the murderers increased in Israel, בטלה עגלה ערופה, batla
eglah arufah, they stopped doing עגלה ערופה eglah arufah because עגלה ערופה
eglah arufah reflected a time when we were basically in control and
this was an aberration and we were dealing with the guilt of
not having letting it get to this point. When there was just
murder all over the land it was seen to be lacking meaning
to try to do this ritual. We'll see more about this in
the גמרא. משיבא אלעזר בן דינאי, mishe-ba Elazar ben Dinai, when אלעזר
בן דינאי Elazar ben Dinai came around,
ותחינה בן פרישה היה נקרא, u-Tchina ben Perisha hayah nikra, his name
was ותחינה בן פרישה, Tchina ben Perisha, חזרו לקראתו בן הרצחן, chazru
likrato ben ha-ratzchan, he was then called the son of the murderer.
Okay, so that was a lot of and this might have to
very much do with the whole period in the end of the
בית שני Bayit Sheini period about the Zelots and about the murdering
one another and so on around those issues. Okay. משרבו המנאפים, mishe-rabu
ha-menafim, once the adulterers became many, פסקו המים המרים, pasku ha-mayim ha-marim,
you stopped using the סוטה sota water because the סוטה Sotah, water
is only when the person, meaning the men now we're talking about,
that they became regular adulterers, so then the water stopped checking the
wives once the men themselves were sinning, so the whole thing was
seen to be meaningless so they stopped doing it. רבן יוחנן בן
זכאי הפסיקן, Rabban Yochanan ben Zakkai hifsikan, it was רבן יוחנן בן
זכאי Rabban Yochanan ben Zakkai who said we should stop bothering with
the water. שנאמר לא אפקוד על בנותיכם כי תזנינה, shene-emar lo efkod
al benoteichem ki tizneina, I will no longer visit upon your daughters
when they sort of fornicate, ועל כלותיכם כי תנאפנה, ve-al kaloteichem ki
tinafna, and because of your daughter-in-laws when they commit adultery. Okay. משמת
יוסי בן יועזר איש צרידה ויוסי בן יהודה איש ירושלים, mishe-meit Yosi
ben Yoezer ish Tsereidah ve-Yosi ben Yehuda ish Yerushalayim, when these two
rabbis died and they were the very very early in the period
of the פרושים, Perushim, if you read פרקי אבות Pirkei Avot they
were right at the beginning and when they died, בטלו האשכולות, batlu
ha-eshkolot, the אשכולות eshkolot which the גמרא will say means like the
rabbis that had were totally complete, had all the wisdom all of
the knowledge in them, that was אשכול eshkol literally means like a
cluster of grapes, that stopped, meaning the future generations were not at
the same level of perfection. And that's why then there started developing
debates because only a very small number of debates earlier on and
then it got greater and greater because the tradition
was broken and there was therefore people were not as fully knowledgeable
as they were in the past. Okay. שנאמר אין אשכול לאכול ביכורה
אותה נפשי. shene-emar ein eshkol le-echol bikurah ivta nafshi. Okay. There is
there no longer the whatever the clusters to eat. Okay. יוחנן כהן
גדול העביר הודית מעשר, Yochanan Kohen Gadol he-evir hodayat ma'aser, יוחנן כהן
גדול Yochanan Kohen Gadol stopped people from doing the תורה says every
three years you say I have gotten rid of the מעשר ma'aser
from the house. We'll see in the גמרא why he stopped that.
ואף הוא ביטל את המעוררים ואת הנוקפים, ve-af hu biteil et ha-me'orerim
ve-et ha-nokfim, and he also caused an end to the מעוררים me'orerim
and the נוקפים, nokfim, we will see what that means in the
גמרא. עד ימיו היה פטיש מכה בירושלים, ad yamav hayah patish makeh
bi-Yerushalayim, until his day you would hear the banging of the hammer
of the anvil in Jerusalem when the
metalworkers, the smelters, and this means during חול המועד Chol HaMoed they
were allowed to do it because if they wouldn't do it it
would be דבר האבד, davar ha-aveid, a thing of serious loss, but
because it was so noisy and everybody heard all this work being
done on חול המועד Chol HaMoed and it undermined the sense that
you're not supposed to do work on חול המועד, Chol HaMoed, he
said you have to stop doing that. ובימיו אין צריך לשאול על
דמאי, u-ve-yamav ein tzarich lish'ol al demai, in his generation
you do not have to ask people about דמאי demai because we'll
see he instituted taking תרומות ומעשרות terumot u-ma'asrot from דמאי. demai. Okay.
So let's take a look.
תנו רבנן מנין שאם נערפה העגלה ואחר כך נמצא ההורג tanu rabanan
minayin she-im neerfa ha-eglah ve-achar kach nimtza ha-horeig אין פוטרין אותו. ein
potrin oso. How do you know if you did the ritual of
עגלה ערופה Egla Arufa and then you found the murderer that he
doesn't get off the hook? תלמוד לומר: Talmud lomar: ולארץ לא יכופר
לדם אשר שופך בה כי אם בדם שופכו, u-la-aretz lo yechupar la-dam
asher shupach bah ki im be-dam shofcho, because the land will not
be atoned without the blood of the one who did the murderer
and therefore in the end the עגלה ערופה Egla Arufa holds you
for the time being but ultimately you need the blood of the
murderer if you could ever find it. Okay. עד אחד אומר ראיתי
את ההורג. Ed echad omer ra'iti es hahoreg. טעמא. Ta'ama. So now
the גמרא saying there's a problem that this sort of... well let's
take a look. טעמא דמכחיש ליה הא לא מכחיש ליה עד אחד
מהימן. Ta'ama demachish leh hai lo machish leh ed echad ne'eman. So
the first thing it sounds is like only because it's one and
one they neutralize, but if only one said unchallenged that I saw
that the murder occur, then you would not go through with the
process. So that's again like the סוטה, Sotah. if you have one
witness that says I saw it happen, you don't go through with
the ritual. מנא הני מילי? Minani mili? Where do you know this
from? דתנו רבנן: Detanu rabbanan: לא נודע מי הכהו, lo noda mi
hikahu, you don't know who smote, who killed this guy. הא נודע,
Ha noda, if it is known מי הכהו mi hikahu אפילו אחד
בסוף העולם לא היו עורפין. afilu echad besof ha'olam lo hayu orfin.
If it's known in any way, meaning not enough to prosecute in
court but it's known in any way, then you would not go
through with this ritual and that's how you know one witness is
believed to say it to the point that you don't go through
with the ritual. רבי עקיבא אומר מנין לסנהדרין שראו אחד שהרג את
הנפש ואין מכירין אותו שלא היו עורפין? Rabbi Akiva omer: Minayin lesanhedrin
sherau echad sheharag es hanefesh ve'ein makkirin oso shelo hayu orfin? How
do you know even if they saw it without knowing who the
murderer was that that would be sufficient to say that you would
not go through with the process? תלמוד לומר: Talmud lomar: ועינינו לא
ראו, ve'eineinu lo rau, because they say our eyes didn't
see. והלא ראו vaha lo rau and now they've seen it. So
now which is interesting. Let's say somebody who isn't a סנהדרין Sanhedrin
saw but didn't identify because by the סנהדרין Sanhedrin they say our
eyes didn't see. By the other פסוק it said it was not
known who did it, מי. So maybe seeing it isn't enough unless
somebody claims that they know who did it. Anyway now the גמרא
says like this.
השתא דאמרת עד אחד מהימן אידך היכי מצי מכחיש? Hashta de'amart ed
echad ne'eman idach hachi matzi machish? Now wait a minute we got
a question though. Okay now we said one is believed so then
how come one and one neutralizes? והאמר עולא. Veha'amar Ulla. Now this
is going to be exact word for word a גמרא we did
before by the עד אחד ed echad of a סוטה. Sotah Didn't
עולא Ulla teach: כל מקום שהאמינה תורה עד אחד הרי כאן שנים
ואין דבריו של אחד במקום שנים? kol makom she'heiminu torah ed echad
harei kan shenayim ve'ein divrei shelo echad bemakom shenayim? That if the
Torah believes the one witness about the עגלה ערופה Egla Arufa or
about the סוטה it has its fully, he's fully believed again not
to prosecute but in terms of this issue of not going through
with the ritual. So if that's true and the one is like
it counts like two and now
another witness afterwards can't neutralize him because the other witness doesn't have
special believability, only the witness who says that they saw has special
believability. וכן אמר... so אמר
ליה עולא Ulla תני לא היו עורפין. lo hayu orfin. Okay he
switched the גרסא girsa in the משנה Mishnah and his גרסא girsa
in the משנה Mishnah is that if it's one against one they
would they would stop the ritual. The one who said he saw
he has greater weight greater believability the one who contradicts him does
not neutralize him, completely changes the פסק psak in the משנה Mishnah
and therefore one against one you believe the one who said he
saw and you do not go through with the process. וכן אמר
רבי יצחק תני לא היו עורפין. Vechayn amar Rabbi Yitzchak tani lo
hayu orfin. Okay so they switched the גרסא. girsa. רבי חייא אמר
תני היו עורפין. Rabbi Chiya amar tani hayu orfin. And רבי חייא
Rabbi Chiya says no come on the משנה Mishnah is like it
says one against one
neutralize. לרבי חייא קשיא דעולא, leRabbi Chiya kashya deUlla, but then what
does רבי חייא Rabbi Chiya do with עולא Ulla because we assume
עולא's Ulla ruling is one that everybody would agree with? So the
גמרא says לא קשיא lo kashya it's not difficult, כאן בבת אחת
כאן בזה אחר זה. kan bevas achas kan bezeh achar zeh. There's
a difference between whether they came at the same time or sequentially.
When they came at the same time in an earlier place רש"י
Rashi says it means תוך כדי דיבור toch kidei dibbur but תוספות
Tosafos says no it just means that they haven't ruled yet on
the first witness. One witness says I saw and then before they
decided to make some ruling that oh you saw we're not going
to do the עגלה ערופה Egla Arufa it was no such formal
acceptance of his, another one came and said no no no you
didn't see you were with me. Okay so in that case you
can neutralize when they're coming at what's considered to be the same
time before the first one got accepted and sort of authorized then
they neutralize. When עולא said the first witness establishes it and cannot
be overrun that's when the first one came and was already accepted.
תנן. tnan. Now let's try to figure out the משנה Mishnah because
the משנה Mishnah sort of confuses because it gives sort of talks
in both extremes.
עד אחד אומר ראיתי את ההורג ושנים אומרים לא ראית היו עורפין.
Ed echad omer ra'iti es hahoreg veshenayim omrim lo ra'isa hayu orfin.
In that case you would go through with it the two would
neutralize. So the גמרא says הא חד וחד לא היו עורפין. ha
chad vechad lo hayu orfin. That sounds like one against one it
wouldn't neutralize. תיובתא דרבי חייא? Tyuvta deRabbi Chiya? That's a contradiction to
רבי חייא Rabbi Chiya because he says one and one would neutralize
assuming it's the same time. So the גמרא says no the משנה
Mishnah is difficult because it gives both cases of two and one
in both extremes and it doesn't make it clear what the case
of one and one is in the middle. ולטעמיך אימא סיפא. Ulta'amech
ayma seifa. Look at the end. שנים אומרים ראינו ואחד אומר לא
ראיתם לא היו עורפין. Shenayim omrim ra'inu ve'echad omer lo ra'isem lo
hayu orfin. Two says we saw and one says you didn't see
לא היו עורפין. So there because the two beat out the one
and they said we saw you would not do it. So that
suggests הא חד וחד היו עורפין. ha chad vechad hayu orfin. That
suggests if it was one and
one that it would neutralize. So now you got a problem the
first part of the משנה Mishnah sounds like if it's two and
one in one direction it's the problem but one and one doesn't
neutralize and the other... The way the משנה *Mishnah* sounds the opposite,
you know, that one and one does neutralize. So which way are
you going to go? אלא מתניתין כולה בפסולי עדות *Ella matnitin kula
bi-psulei edut*. So the משנה *Mishnah* really, you have to understand, is
not talking, it talks about people that are פסולי עדות *psulei edut*.
וכדרבי נחמיה *U-ki-derabi Nechemya*, like רבי נחמיה *Rabi Nechemya*, דאמר *de-amar* who
says כל מקום שהאמינה תורה עד אחד הלך אחר רוב דעות *kol
makom she-heimina Torah ed echad halech achar rov deot*. Anytime the Torah
believed one witness, it does not have the weight of a formal
two witnesses. Even though one is like two when it's believed, it's
not with the formality of two witnesses. The formality of two witnesses
is once you have two, two counts like a hundred. Here in
the end, you know, it is just ultimately going to be a
numbers game. Okay, he said הלך אחר רוב דעות *halech achar rov
deot*. ועשו שתי נשים באיש אחד כשני אנשים באיש אחד *Ve-asu shtei
nashim be-ish echad ki-shnei anashim be-ish echad*. Okay, and therefore, if you
have one man that says I saw who killed and two women
say you don't, because since one man is not two witnesses, he's
only one witness. Even though he's a כשר *kosher* witness and he's
a man, two even of פסול *pasul*, two women still beat out
one man and they neutralize. So the reason the משנה *Mishnah* was
saying two against one neutralize is not to say that one against
one wouldn't neutralize, but it's to tell you the חידוש *chiddush* that,
you know, that even פסולי עדות *psulei edut*, even, you know, women
will neutralize one man. Okay. ואיכא דאמרי *Ve-ika de-amri* and some say
כל היכא דאתא עד אחד מעיקרא אפילו מאה נשים כחד דמי *kol
heicha de-ata ed echad me-ikara afilu meah nashim ke-chad dami*. Actually no,
that's not true. If the first witness that testified was a man
and he said I saw and the Torah gives special believability to
say you saw, then that man counts like two real halakhic witnesses
and two כשר *kosher* witnesses would, you know, neutralize, but women would
not neutralize that. והכא סבר *Ve-hacha savar* how do you explain the
two neutralizing the one in the משנה *Mishnah*? והכא במאי עסקינן *Ve-hacha
be-mai askinan* what are we talking about? כגון דאתא אישה מעיקרא *kegon
de-ata ishah me-ikara* that it's all פסול *pasul* witnesses. One woman against
two women in both ways. So basically what we're saying is like
this. The משנה *Mishnah* is complicated because the משנה *Mishnah* says one
against one neutralizes, at least that's our גירסא *girsa* although, you know,
the גמרא *Gemara* like, you know, re-reads it. שמואל *Shmuel* re-reads it.
But then it says two against one the two wins, one against,
you know, and then another two against one the other two wins
and it leaves us confusing what's the one against one. Why do
you have to say two against one in both directions? Like, you
know, so it's a very confusing משנה *Mishnah* about what is the
standard case about one against one, does it neutralize or not? And
the גמרא *Gemara* said the cases about two against one are cases
to tell you a חידוש *chiddush* about פסול *pasul* witnesses. Two women
neutralize one either even one man according to one read or, okay,
a one woman, that one man, that would be different. But either
way, the point is not to get at the issue of one
man against one man or say something of that nature, it's to
tell you a הלכה *halakha* that פסולי עדות *psulei edut*, you know,
you know, in this case they count two against one. Okay, so
it says like this, where
was I? Okay, ותרצה לרבי נחמיה הכי *Ve-tirtza le-Rabi Nechemya hachi*. And
here's what רבי נחמיה *Rabi Nechemya* says. רבי נחמיה אומר *Rabi Nechemya
omer* כל מקום שהאמינה תורה עד אחד *kol makom she-heimina Torah ed
echad* when the Torah believes one witness הלך אחר רוב דעות *halech
achar rov deot* go by the majority numbers when you're dealing with
פסולי עדות *psulei edut*. ועשו שתי נשים באשה אחת כשני אנשים באיש
אחד *Ve-asu shtei nashim be-ishah achat ki-shnei anashim be-ish echad*. Two women
against one woman is like two men against one man. Okay, so
as long as they're all פסול *pasul* or they're all כשר *kasher*,
the numbers win out or two wins out against one. אבל שתי
נשים באיש אחד כי פלגא ופלגא דמי *Aval shtei nashim be-ish echad
ki palga u-palga dami*. That would be considered to be not winning
out and that would just be like one against one and if
the one man said he saw then because the one man has
special believability he would win. ותרי פסולי עדות למה לי *Ve-trei psulei
edut lama li*? So now why do I need to tell me
go by the two whether the two are saying they saw or
the two are saying they didn't see? מהו דתימא כי אזלינן בתר
רוב דעות לחומרא *Mahu de-teima ki azlinan batar rov deot le-chumra* maybe
you would just listen to the two to be strict, you know,
let's say not to do the breaking of the neck. אבל לקולא
לא *Aval le-kula lo*. קא משמע לן *Ka mashma lan* that you
would. So this whole גמרא *Gemara* is really identical to the גמרא
*Gemara* we did about two weeks ago on this topic. And at
the end of the day the point, the takeaway point is that
when one witness says they saw, whether it's the adultery or the
עגלה ערופה *eglah arufah*, that witness is believed and you do not
go ahead and do it. And if that witness is accepted first
then certainly one witness that come after cannot neutralize. Can two witnesses
come after and neutralize? It depends. If it's one man then two
men can neutralize. If it's one woman then two women can neutralize.
If it is one man against two women who come later then
that depends on the different readings of רבי נחמיה *Rabi Nechemya*. Okay,
we will stop here.